Finding Aid for the American Art Association Records, 1877-1924 MS.15
The Frick Collection/Frick Art Reference Library Archives
- Series II: Correspondence and Notes, 1877-1924
  - De Kay, Charles, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Letters to Charles de Kay. Correspondents include Frank P. Crasto, Jr., P. Whitwell Wilson, Arthur Swann of the American Art Association, John S. Wood, Henry Rood, Eugenio Pirani, R.W. van Boskerck, and John De Kay regarding the U.S. preventing his entry into the country and complaints about Washington. Also a few letters criticizing book reviews he has written.
  - Emmons, Arthur B., 1919-1922 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
    Correspondence between Emmons and Kirby regarding public sale at Emmons' residence at 60 Park Avenue on August 28, 1919; sale of etchings on December 4-5, 1919; sale of Emmons' Renoirs and Monets, January 14-15, 1920; and his subsequent repurchase of one of Monet's "poppy pictures" from Durand-Ruel.
  - Inness, George - Essay, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Handwritten essay by Thomas Kirby about the American Art Association's relationship with George Inness.
  - Notes, miscellaneous, 1898, undated (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
    Descriptions of auction sales, private collections, and miscellaneous notes.
  - Whistler Pictures, Correspondence as to the Sale of, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Carbon copies of correspondence between Sir George Lewis and Joseph Pennell regarding the disposition of Whistler engravings and prints belonging to the estate of William Heinemann.
- Series III: Clippings, 1881-1924
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  The bulk of the newspaper articles concern auction sales of the American Art Association, the 1922 opening of the new galleries on 57th Street, and the sale of Rosa Bonheur's Horse Fair in 1887. Also contains articles on the history of the American Art Association, Thomas Kirby, Gustavus Kirby, Rose Lorenz, auction sales of other galleries, private collections and an obituary of Charles Freer. Newspaper clippings were photocopied onto acid free paper.
  - American Art Association - Auction Sales, 1885-1895; 1921-1923 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    Folder 1 contains photocopies of the newspaper clippings; Folder 2 contains the originals (some originals removed to oversize).
  - American Art Association - History, 1896, 1922; hi (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - American Art Association - New Galleries, 30 East 57th Street, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 4-6)
    Re opening and Fifth Avenue Association Prize.
    [3 folders, 2 of originals]
  - Bonheur, Rosa, 1887 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Regarding purchase of Horse Fair at A.T. Stewart sale of March 23, 1887-March 31, 1887 by Cornelius Vanderbilt and his subsequent donation of the painting to the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
  - Freer, Charles L., 1919 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Obituary
  - Kirby, Gustavus, 1922-1923 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Kirby, Thomas, 1896-1922, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Lorenz, Rose, 1916, 1923 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1881-1924 (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
    Articles about auction sales, private collections, and works of art.